Sandra Dolby papers, 1960-2010 C695
Indiana University Archives
Sandra Dolby papers
1960-2010
1990-2009
Indiana University Archives
Dolby, Sandra K., 1946-
C695
2.6 cubic feet 4 boxes
Sandra Dolby is an alumna and faculty member of the department of Folklore and Ethnomusicology at Indiana University. She taught Folklore courses at IU from 1979 to 2010, during which time she also taught American Studies at Norway as a Fulbright Traveling Scholar. The collection reflects her interests in pedagogy, American Studies, and the application of literary theory to the study of folklore and personal narrative. It contains syllabi and teaching materials, manuscripts and presentations about her research, and documents from her service in and out of the university, as well as biographical materials.
Access Restrictions
Select files closed to researchers due to the presence of confidential student and employment information; these are indicated in the folder list.
Advance notice required for access to collection.
Biographical Note
Sandra K. Dolby was born in 1946 and received a BA in English from Manchester College in 1969. After a period of teaching high school English, she received her master's degree (1973) and PhD (1975) from the Folklore and Ethnomusicology Department at Indiana University. As a doctoral student, she studied her family's folklore and how literary scholarship could help explain the genre of personal experience narratives, which led to her first book, Literary Folkloristics and the Personal Narrative (1989).
After graduating, Dolby worked briefly in the English department at the University of Houston before returning to IU as an Assistant Professor in 1979. During her tenure at IU, she was Acting Director of American Studies from 1994 to 1995 and Director of the Folklore Institute from 2007 to 2008. She spent several years doing research internationally, receiving a fellowship from the National Libraries in Australia in 1985 and spending 2001 to 2002 as a Fulbright Roving Scholar of American Studies in Norway. In a service capacity, she was the Director of Undergraduate Studies in the Folklore and Ethnomusicology Department, taught folklore pedagogy, was on the advisory committee for the School of Teaching and Learning, and co-chaired the AI Committee as part of her work on the Bloomington Faculty Committee. After retiring from IU in 2010, she worked in the Department of English at the University of Houston. Throughout her academic career, Dr. Dolby also maintained a love of music: she sang, recorded, and composed folksongs, jazz, and choral works, and produced several albums.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into five series:
Biographical materials
Conference presentations and manuscripts
Teaching
Grant applications and related materials
Service
Scope and Content Note
This collection spans the years 1960-2009 and documents folklist and professor Sandra K. Dolby's scholarly activities including research, publications, and presentations on tall tales, proverbs, and other folklore topics; grant activities; teaching and student advising; and professional service. The bulk of the collection originates from Dolby's time as a faculty member in the Indiana University Folklore Institute and later the Department of Folklore.
Types of material held in the collection include notes, publications and drafts, correspondence, grant applications, syllabi and lesson plans, committee files, letters of recommendation, and audiovisual material.
The collection is arranged into five series: Biographical materials; Publications, presentations, and workshops; Teaching; Grant applications and related research materials; and Service.
Related Material
Additional publications and research materials may be accessed in IUScholarworks.
Related photographs may be available in the University Archives Photographs Database.
Acquisition Information
Accessions 2012/021 and 2015/033
Provenance
Collection was donated by Sandra Dolby in 2012 and 2015.
Appraisal
Article printouts that didn't include annotations; graded student assignments; and unmarked chapters of dissertations submitted for Dolby's review were removed and destroyed.
- Biographical materials, 1964-2008
  Scope and Content Note
  This series includes liner notes and CDs Sandra Dolby collected and produced, as well as departmental folklore event programs.
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged chronologically.
  - Fine Times Notes, 1964 (Box 1)
  - Event Programs, 1965-2003 (Box 1)
  - Letter from a student, 1981 (Box 1)
  - Dolby Genealogy, 2000 (Box 1)
  - Personal papers, 2000-2001 (Box 1)
  - London Trip – Easter 2002 (Box 1)
  - When I Wanted Warm Liner Notes, 2005 (Box 1)
  - Paul Jackson Sermons, undated (Box 1)
  - Musical Recordings (Box 1)
    - Tunes from My Father's Radio by Sandy Dolby, undated; (compact disc) (Box 4)
    - First Time Ever by Sandy Dolby, undated; (compact disc) (Box 4)
    - Those Were the Days – Christmas '13 by Sandy Dolby and Ilze Akerbergs, undated; (compact disc) (Box 4)
    - Wedding Song by Sandy Dolby, undated; (compact disc) (Box 4)
    - Souvenirs – Songs from my Mother's Attic by Sandy Dolby; Ilze Akerbergs piano and CD production, undated; (compact disc) (Box 4)
    - We Learned a Lot of Songs Along the Way – W.D. Collins 1892-1976 parts 1 and 2 by W.D. Collins, undated; (2 compact discs) (Box 4)
- Publications, presentations, and workshops, 1975-2009
  - Sandra Dolby offprints, 1975-2005 (Box 1)
  - George Webbe Dasent, 1980-1987 (Box 1)
  - Pack Carnes articles, 1981-1992 (Box 1)
  - Stories of a Safe Adventure: Americans Living in Australia American Folklore Society, circa 1982 (Box 1)
  - American Folklore Society, 1990-1991 (Box 1)
  - Personal Proverbs, Slogans, and Life Stories, CFS, 1990-1991 (Box 1)
  - Proverbs, Slogans, and Worldview in Popular Nonfiction, American Folklore Society, 1993 (Box 1)
  - Disney Paper, 1994 (Box 1)
  - Johnny Appleseed, 1998 (Box 1)
    File includes a 1964 Classics Illustrated Junior "Johnny Appleseed" comic.
  - Personal Folklore book, 1998 (Box 1)
  - American Folklore in Norwegian Schools, Hoosier Folklore Society, 2001-2002 (Box 1)
  - What's this Story About the Boyfriend's Death Doing in My American History Textbook?: Contemporary Legends, American History, and Secondary Education, American Folklore Society, 2002 (Box 1)
  - Berea, Kentucky, project/workshop, 2003; (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - East o' the Sun: Constant, Variable, and the Cultural Frame of Reference, American Folklore Society, 2003; (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - East o' the Sun/overheads, Hoosier Folklore Society, 2003 (Box 1)
  - What Arnold Lobel Knew and Admired about Fables---and What He Didn't, American Folklore Society, 2004 (Box 1)
  - Cultural Plagiarism, 2005 (Box 1)
  - Personal Narrative book use, 2005 (Box 1)
  - Tall Tale draft, 2005 (Box 1)
  - Who is Your Guru?, 2005 (Box 1)
  - An Annie Oakley Video, Folklore, and American Worldview, American Folklore Society, 2006 (Box 1)
  - Self-Help Books: Why Americans Keep Reading Them IU Mini-University, 2007 (Box 1)
  - Tall Tale and Legend Notes, 2007 (Box 1)
  - What Would Dorson Do? And Why Should We Care? (Old Stormalong paper), 2007 (Box 1)
  - Course Development Institute, 2008; (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - From Paul Bunyan to Mrs. Knowsit: the Creation and Use of Pedagogical Hero Tales American Folklore Society, 2008 (Box 1)
  - Mose, Popular Sources, and Calling it Folklore, Western States Folklore Society, 2008 (Box 1)
  - Self-Help Book Lecture, 2008 (Box 1)
  - Folktales as Self-Help Narratives American Folklore Society, 2009 (Box 1)
  - Copyright workshop info, undated (Box 1)
- Grant applications and related research materials, 1990-2006
  This series is arranged into three subseries: General, Fulbright lectures and presentation materials, and Traveling scholar visits. The general subseries is arranged chronologically according to when each project began, and includes applications and orientation materials for several scholarships. The second and third subseries primarily consist of documents related to Dolby's two years in Norway as a Fulbright traveling scholar, where she worked with secondary school teachers on how to use folklore as a tool when teaching American studies and history. The lectures subseries is arranged alphabetically and includes her specific lesson plans for this subject, while the Traveling scholar visit files are arranged chronologically and include correspondence with teachers and travel documentation for each school she visited.
  - General, 1997-2006 (Box 2)
    - Fulbright (Box 2)
      - Norway, 2000-2001 (Box 2)
      - Fulbright Information, Mike's Calendar, 2001 (Box 2)
      - Office Expense Receipts, 2001 (Box 2)
      - Oslo Living Information, 2001 (Box 2)
      - 2002 Fulbright Seminar, 2001-2002 (Box 2)
    - Norway (Box 2)
      - School Seminar Schedule, 1997-2001 (Box 2)
      - Human Subjects Info, 2000-2001 (Box 2)
    - Dasent (Box 2)
      - Dasent Project, 2001 (Box 2)
      - NEH Dasent, 2005 (Box 2)
      - NEH Application, 2005-2006 (Box 2)
    - Trip to Germany, March 9-13, 2002 (Box 2)
    - Tall Tale Project, 2006 (Box 2)
  - Fulbright lecture and presentation materials, 1990-2002
    - American Studies Association of Norway (ASANOR) - Folklore Paper, 2001 (Box 2)
    - Self-Help Paper, 2001 (Box 2)
    - Big Map of Nations, circa 2001 (Box 2)
    - Children's Folklore, circa 2001 (Box 2)
    - Diversity, 2001 (Box 2)
    - Extra Handouts - Various, circa 2001 (Box 2)
    - Gender, 2001 (Box 2)
    - General Concepts, Themes/Outlines, circa 2001 (Box 2)
    - Immigration, Settlement, Slavery, 2001 (Box 2)
    - Native Americans, 1990-2001 (Box 2)
    - Religion/Belief, 2001 (Box 2)
    - Talk on Self Help (U of Oslo, ), 2002 (Box 2)
    - Values and Worldviews, 2001 (Box 2)
    - Violence, 2001-2002 (Box 2)
  - Traveling scholar visits, 2001-2002
    - Expense Forms, 2001 (Box 2)
    - Bergen (Lynghaug skole) C: Rimmereide, 2001 (Box 2)
    - Oslo (As skole) C: Aspelund, 2001 (Box 2)
    - Oslo (Skoyenasen skole) C: Hansen, 2001 (Box 2)
    - Hjartdal (Telemark) [Sauland] C: Granlund, 2001 (Box 2)
    - Osen – near Namsos (Trondheim) C: Sundet, 2001 (Box 2)
    - Oslo (Tonsberg) Byskogen Sk. C: Godaker, 2001 (Box 2)
    - Stavanger (International School) C: Duevel, 2001 (Box 2)
    - Alta C: Bang, 2001 (Box 2)
    - Malselv (south of Tromso) C: Oygarden, 2001 (Box 2)
    - Bodo (Hunstad Ungdomskole) C: Stein, 2001 (Box 2)
    - Trondheim – Trondsk, Laerarstemne C: Tanem, October 3-4, 2001 (Box 2)
    - Rissa (near Trondheim) C: Lillevik, October 8-10, 2001 (Box 2)
    - Oslo (Hosletoppen skole) C: Johansen, October 15, 2001 (Box 2)
    - Kristiansand – Sorlandsk Laerersterne C: Estensen, October 19, 2001 (Box 2)
    - Lodingen (Tromso) C: Olsen/Ytterstad, October 22, 2001 (Box 2)
    - Oslo (Teachers Conf.) C: Olsnes, October 26, 2001 (Box 2)
    - Oslo (Bjornhoff) C: Wroldsen, October 29, 2001 (Box 2)
    - Svalbard (Longyearbyon Sk) C: Misje, October 31 – November 3, 2001 (Box 2)
    - Bergen (West Norway T Conf.) C: Nagel, November 9, 2001 (Box 2)
    - Stavanger (Sandnes) C: Engseth, November 15, 2001 (Box 2)
    - Stavanger (Teachers Conf.) C: Rullestad, November 15-16, 2001 (Box 2)
    - Hatlestand (near Bergen) C: Nerhus, 19 November, 2001 (Box 2)
    - Tofte (near Drammen) C: Nederhoed, November 26, 2001 (Box 2)
    - Kristiansand (Grim Skole) C: Knatsen, November 28, 2001 (Box 2)
    - Trondheim (Blussvoll) C: Solberg, December 4-5, 2001 (Box 2)
    - Steinkjer (no. of Trondheim) C: Nielsen, December 6-7, 2001 (Box 2)
    - Risor (between Oslo/Kvitesied) C: Naess, February 5, 2002 (Box 2)
    - Stjordal (Stokkan skole) C: Moa, February 18-19, 2002 (Box 2)
    - Namas (Nord-Trondelag) C: Roset, 2001-2002 (Box 2)
    - Hitre (near Trondheim) C: Gjolmesli, February 21, 2002 (Box 2)
    - Harstad (Tromso) C: Lyngfoss, February 25-26, 2002 (Box 2)
    - Trysil (near Swedish border) C: Martinsen, February 28, 2002 (Box 2)
    - Rodsberg (Halden) C: Fleitscher, March 5, 2002 (Box 2)
    - Porsgrunn (near Skien) C: Lyons, March 6, 2002 (Box 2)
    - Kristiansand (Pedag. Ctr.) C: Osthassel, March 14-15, 2002 (Box 2)
    - Buskerud – [Honefoss] C: Coldevin, April 12, 2002 (Box 2)
    - Lyngseidet (near Tromso) C: Figenschou, April 18-19, 2002 (Box 2)
    - Hammerfest (North) C: Lager, April 22, 2002 (Box 2)
    - Kristiansund, C: Dahl, April 24-25, 2002 (Box 2)
    - Brattvag (near Alesund) C: Sandnes, April 26, 2002 (Box 2)
    - Midtstuen skole (Oslo) C: Mo, April 29, 2002 (Box 2)
    - Oslo (Gorudel) C: Olsnes, May 2, 2002 (Box 2)
    - Oslo (Tonsberg) [HoFSkole] C: Arntzen/Nilsen, 2002 (Box 2)
- Teaching, 1988-2009
  The Teaching series includes syllabi, overheads, lecture notes, student assignments, and other materials Dolby used in her courses. Of particular interest are the consent forms, writing assignments, personal journals, and VHS recordings of a class discussion collected while teaching F420/F545. This was a course on folk narrative and the materials produced were used as part of a research project conducted through the School of Teaching and Learning.
  This series is arranged alphabetically by folklore course number.
  - F101 Introduction to Folklore (Box 1)
    - Overheads, 2003 (Box 1)
    - Rhonda Dass F101, 2003-2004 (Box 1)
    - Jenn Horn F101, 2003-2004 (Box 1)
    - Paul Schauert F101, 2003-2004 (Box 1)
    - AI Meetings, 2004 (Box 1)
    - Unit – F101, 2004-2010 (Box 1)
    - 2003-2005 (Box 1)
    - Intro to Folklore, 2003-2005 (Box 1)
    - 2003-2005 (Box 1)
    - Printer's Hat, circa 2005 (Box 1)
    - Introduction to Folklore, 2010 (Box 1)
  - F320 Australian Folklore, 2006 (Box 1)
  - F420/F545 Survey of Folk Narrative and School of Teaching and Learning (SOTL) Project (Box 1)
    - 2003 (Box 1)
    - SOTL – 2003 Human Subject, 2003-2005 (Box 1)
    - Human Subject, 2003 (Box 1)
    - Consent Forms, 2003 (Box 1)
    - Storytelling Assignment #1, 2003 (Box 1)
    - Storytelling Assignment #2, 2003 (Box 1)
    - Storytelling Assignment #3, 2003 (Box 1)
    - Reflexive Essay, 2003 (Box 1)
    - SOTL – Final Statement, 2003 (Box 1)
    - Student Journals, 2003; (2 folders) (Box 1)
    - Student Journals, 2003 (Box 2)
    - Video of a class discussion, parts 1-3, 2003; (3 VHS tapes) (Box 4)
    - 2006 (Box 2)
    - 2009 (Box 2)
  - F497 Advanced Seminar (Box 2)
    - Seminar for Majors, 1998 (Box 2)
    - 2001 (Box 2)
    - Course Prep Materials, 2003-2005 (Box 2)
  - F501/512 Colloquy (Box 2)
    - Readings, 1984-2001 (Box 2)
    - 2004 (Box 2)
    - 2006 (Box 2)
    - 2005-2009 (Box 2)
  - F625/G620 Folklore in American Studies, 2002 (Box 2)
  - F734: Storytelling, Cultural framing, and Reading Folklore, Spring 2008 (Box 2)
  - F740: The Personal and the Everyday in Folklore, 1998-1999 (Box 2)
  - F801: Teaching Folklore and Ethnomusicology, 2006-2009 (Box 2)
  - Genre List/Lecture, 2003-2009 (Box 2)
  - Teaching Overheads, circa 1998 (Box 2)
- Service, 1981-2009
  This aeries is further organized into five subseries which are arranged chronologically. The five subseries are A.I. training and teaching observations, Folklore and ethnomusicology faculty affairs, IU committees and service, Mentoring, and the Tall Tales project. The first three subseries include teaching observations, dissertation proposals with comments from Dr. Dolby, correspondence related to letters of recommendation, and official meeting notes for committees within the Folklore department and the university as a whole. The last subseries includes articles and programs she reviewed for groups outside of the campus and the scripts she reviewed for a children's television show based on tall tales.
  - Folklore and Ethnomusicology faculty affairs, 1981-2008
    - 1981 Journal of Folklore Institute (JFI) schedule (Box 2)
    - Faculty Meetings, 2004-2006 (Box 2)
    - Faculty Affairs, 2005 (Box 2)
      Separated Materials
      (Restricted material removed and stored separately)
    - Faculty Affairs, 2005 (Box 4)
      Conditions Governing Access
      (RESTRICTED)
    - Folklore Institute Faculty, 2007-2008 (Box 2)
      This notebook includes faculty and one-on-one meeting notes
    - Notebook, 2008 (Box 2)
      This notebook contains notes about faculty affairs for Folklore and Ethnomusicology
    - Linda Dégh Bio, 2008 (Box 2)
    - Dick and Henry Retirement, 2008 (Box 2)
  - IU Committees and Service, 1999-2007
    - IUPUI Master of Library Science (MLS), 1999 (Box 2)
    - A.I. Affairs Committee, 2004-2005 (Box 2)
    - Bloomington Faculty Council (BFC) – A.I. Affairs, 2004-2005 (Box 2)
    - Community Outreach and Partnerships in Service-Learning (COPSL), 2005-2006 (Box 2)
    - Individualized Major Program (IMP), 2005 (Box 4)
    - Policy Committee, 2005 (Box 2)
    - College Policy Committee (CPC) – Non-Tenure Faculty Policy, 2006 (Box 2)
    - Faculty Library Use Survey, 2006 (Box 2)
    - Budget meetings, 2007 (Box 3)
  - Mentoring, A.I. training, and teaching observations, 1993-2009
    - Matt Bradley - AI, 1998-1999 (Box 4)
    - Melinda Collins - AI F131, 1998-1999 (Box 4)
    - Terry Parker, 1993-2004 (Box 4)
    - Sheryl Narahara, 1999 (Box 3)
    - A.I. Workshop 2004 (Box 3)
    - Midori's Chapter, 2004 (Box 3)
    - 2004/5/6 Teaching Observations (Box 4)
    - Letters of Reference, 2005 (Box 3)
    - A.I. Training, 2007 (Box 3)
    - David McDonald, 2009 (Box 4)
  - Tall Tale Project, 2004-2005
    - Tall Tale Project, 2004 (Box 3)
    - Pecos Bill – TD Media, 2004 (Box 3)
    - Paul Bunyan Script, 2004 (Box 3)
    - Old Stormalong Script, 2004 (Box 3)
    - John Henry Script, 2004 (Box 3)
    - Davy Crockett Script, 2004 (Box 3)
    - Johnny Appleseed, 2004 (Box 3)
    - Mose Script, 2004 (Box 3)
    - Annie Oakley Script, 2004 (Box 3)
    - Regional Tales – Script, 2005 (Box 3)
    - Mrs. Knowsit – Final Script, 2005 (Box 3)